software engineering radio episode 33 so
our part to be
[Music]
hey welcome to another episode of
software engineering radio this is so
art to be which means it's the
continuation of so our to a which has
been the most recent episode so we're
just going to continue where we left off
last time have fun ok let's talk about
service reuse so of course the idea of
building an SOA often goes along with
the idea of standardizing and
harmonizing all kinds of things data
structures middleware or whatever the
point I'm going to make is that it is
really very useful to standardize on the
metal level right to agree on what is a
component how do we scribe a service
interface how complex can our data be so
this is the the standardization on the
metal level so your complete Enterprise
agrees on the meta models required for
describing the concrete applications and
services and stuff however on the
concrete level it's not that easy to
standardize things for example assume
you want to agree that a service on a
service that returns customer
information for a specific customer ID
ok so we discussed before that you
you'll run into problems firstly because
you'd have to agree enterprise-wide
what this data structure looks like but
even if you could agree on that you
still have probably clients that have
different quality of service
requirements for example the call center
requires the data once they query your
your new service they require the result
very quickly but they only need a few
data attributes the rest can be lazily
loaded if required other clients might
require more data all the time so they
want to have the data in one call
instead of having five different
subsequent calls in order to retrieve
all the less rest because that would
make things slower in the end so the
point is even if you can agree on the
data structure you probably still have
different services that only need
different views on this data and that's
what you mentioned before ever hot you
need different views on the same data
structure so the point is that the
harmonization of interfaces of data
structures will not
really work easily in practice if only
because you have to consider versioning
and and data a migration over time but
that's a different thing so to address
this topic of of views on data and
variability in data structures for
different clients in order to address
this systematically you should consider
a product line approach specifically I'd
recommend to explicitly describe the
variability in the views of the data
structure between different clients now
there is a technique called feature
modeling that can be used to describe
variabilities it's something we'll
discuss in the context of our product
line engineering series of episodes in
the future so I'll just explain very
briefly and I'm not going to talk about
the specific notation the point is that
you will describe that you have
basically have a data structure for
example the dot data for your CRM system
it contains a customer it contains a
customer's basic data like name first
name birth date and it contains an
address for example a shipping address
and a billing address for your customer
also a customer can have billing
information which would be a credit
rating and some invoicing history
finally a customer might be associated
with a number of autos each orders
obviously has a number of items now the
point is what you want to do is you want
to describe the variability how
different clients can see this data
structure for example there might be one
client which if you asked for the
customer information it only returns for
example the customer and it's basic data
right another client if it asks for the
customer information once they have the
customer its shipping address and all
its autos and a third system might want
to see its credit rating and it's
invoicing history what you want to do is
you want to have a formal model that
describes the various views on this data
and you want to associate specific
clients with certain views on this data
so you could say that it's possible that
a client only gets a shipping address
but you know if if it asks for billing
data it either gets the credit rating or
the invoicing history and by associating
this variability model in the form of
feature model with the you know
the overall data structure and saying
that if you have this partial if you
have this variant selected then you'll
get only these aspects of the data you
can using this technique you can you can
you can you can keep control of the
variability that the different clients
need and I'm not going to talk about
more about this now because that's
something we'll talk about in much more
detail in context of this variability
stuff in the product line engineering
stuff okay yeah so so what you're saying
is that for each dead truck should also
model the views that one can have and
model the dependencies on the level of
those that's basically it that that's
kind of what I said in a nutshell yes
okay let's discuss a little bit about
process issues and that's not I'm not
talking about business process issues
here but rather about how you develop
this stuff first of all something that
I've seen happening in several
organizations is that you have to
describe all the services a centralized
service repository and some kind of
heavyweight centralized process that
means if I want to try add an attribute
to my customer description I have to
check into this centralized service
repository you know check change stuff
and then probably fill out five forms
with some central IT department this is
very frustrating for people to work with
because developers have to be online all
the time to access the repository and
they have to coordinate every change for
the whole company to maybe develop just
change something simple in a service so
this kills productivity and makes
development quite unnatural so what you
need to do it's obviously quite obvious
but many people don't do it you should
make sure that service definition
implementation and test can be done
locally without any access to the
central repository and this repository
should use a CVS like check-in/check-out
metaphor to support offline work I don't
want to be connected to the central
service repository if I try to you know
if your prototype some service in the
train while driving to the other office
of my company the coordination with the
central processes you know like clearing
some data
structures or whatever should only
become necessary once when the service
becomes public so you should have like a
status model for your models like you
know as long as something you define its
developer local you can do everything
you want you can define your own data
structures as you want you can define
your own services but you will not be
able to publish and to run this kind of
the service on this global enterprise
service the bus you can only run it
locally on your notebook or whatever and
then you can then once you you know once
you run your unit tests you can then
make this data this model and this this
code basically repository global that
says that everybody else can see it and
then it has to conform to certain you
know enterprise-wide standards like
naming conventions data type structures
whatever and then you could you know
move it to the staging environment into
the production environment I actually
think that the analogy that you have
towards versioning system is quite
interesting because basically what you
are describing is the same thing as
optimistic locking and pessimistic yeah
yeah currency control yes no versioning
system and it's basically the same
scenario people use pessimistic
concurrency control in versioning
systems because they believe that
otherwise the conflicts between the
different developers are not cannot be
resolved and they only they want to make
absolutely sure that only one guy is
working on it and that generates a
bottleneck by definition and that's
basically what what you describe with
the approach to the central repository
as well use an optimistic concurrency
control and try to enforce standards and
so on when when you check stuff in to
the repository and use the optimistic
absolutely control point one last thing
here of course once services have gone
into production and are used you can't
easily change them so you can't change a
service that has been published what you
have to do is of course you have to
define a new version of that service and
then deploy the new version
since we have also the required service
dependencies in our model we can kind of
garbage collect our components you know
we now know once nobody depends on them
on these components anymore and then we
can under ploy the service we can only
under ply the service if nobody else
requires it and by using versioning
nicely in models and and keeping track
of these things and having dependencies
in reversed in the reverse direction
this is really a good thing so we can
now in a controlled manner
you know if evolve services by defining
new versions and get rid of the old
stuff once we know that nobody's using
it anymore or we can you know notify the
old users and say hey you should migrate
to this new version of the service yeah
deprecated
yeah deprecated exactly then let's talk
a little bit about infrastructure versus
application development as I said before
often the introduction of an SOA is
driven by some central IT department
because they want to standardize and
harmonize all the IT infrastructure so
consequently you'll probably have a
focus on middleware and technologies my
recent customer were was they had these
meetings with IBM and with Sun who tried
to sell them on jbi and SCA and all that
stuff and there anyway however the point
is that application developers have
different goals usually you have the
central IT department in a company or an
enterprise and you have a set of you
know business departments which also
develop applications that have to work
well with the other way so of course
they have other requirements they don't
really care about standardization they
have to get there to be developed
applications out of the box out of the
door as soon as possible and they have
to satisfy the business requirements of
their stakeholders so there is a
conflict of interest application
developers don't see benefits when using
the SOA their life typically becomes
more complicated because they now have
to adapt to all those Enterprise white
standards so you'll get a slow adoption
curve of as a way that's a bad thing so
to change that you have to really make
sure that the SOA has advantages for the
application developers their life has to
become easier not more complicated so
you have to make sure that developing
correct
locations correct with correct I mean
applications that are consistent with
the SOA principles constraints and
guidelines you have to make that process
as simple as possible and you have to
hide in order to to ensure that you
first of all have to hide all the so our
technology as far as possible
these people should be able to implement
prototypes of the services as I said
before without caring about the
enterprise wide whatever so what you
need to provide for these customers for
these developers is good
tooling they need to be able to you know
they need to have a modeling tool where
they just draw their services and stuff
press a couple of buttons and after half
an hour they're ready to test their
application logic Service compliant on
the local machine it's not yet deployed
Enterprise why that's different but the
development of the business logic should
be as painless as possible and
implementing correct applications should
be made as easy as possible and that
requires good tool support so you always
have to take your develops with you and
provide nice tools that make them more
productive so for example obviously
you'd for example support you know if
you're in an eclipse-based world you'd
provide an IDE plug-in that generates
the skeleton codes based on the models
and once your models are kind of
official they can generate the glue code
so the stuff can run on some you know
enterprise class platforms but this the
prerequisite of that is that everybody
uses the same ID and everybody uses same
language right no I mean the point is if
you have several languages or several
IDE siient then you need several
generators and or several plugins so I
mean yeah this is more work but it's not
a showstopper at all I mean we have
generated for C++ Android Java the
necessary stops and skeletons and
service glue code and stuff so that's
not a real problem
of course the more heterogeneous your
your landscape is the more work it is
yeah but I get the impression that often
in real enterprises there is nothing at
all the people ever standardize on and
what you're saying here is they should
standardize
and have better support for the resume
and it's still if you wanna get away and
you don't standardize on anything you're
not going to get an s away yeah okay so
so so I mean you have to standardize on
the metamodel on certain technologies at
some point not yet but at some point
you'll have to standardize on a limited
set although not one a limited set of
programming languages and so on so I
mean yes it requires some
standardization I mean so what you so
what you're saying is probably that you
should enforce the standardization on
the people but rather make it something
that is worthwhile
that makes their life easier you
shouldn't require them to do something
strange you should tell them hey here is
this new paradigm and we have this nice
documentation and/or tool support and
implementing an application of the kind
they want to do actually gets easier not
more complicated than before and that
usually requires some kind of tool
support and I mean I'm not saying that
you should standardize everything but
that the paradigm based on which you
develop applications should be
standardized and of course if people
don't want to use these generators or
tools you provide they can still do
everything from from you know manually
by hand because in the end of course you
check conformity once you deploy right
let's take a short look at legacy code
the stuff we talked about before is
obviously especially nice and useful for
new services but you can also use it for
legacy code you can for example you can
basically reverse engineer you know your
your COBOL systems or whatever or your
Java interfaces and generate service
interfaces from that you know assuming
your legacy applications are in some
ways structured which is often not the
case but if they're in some ways
structured you can then of course the
reverse engineer these structures and
derive the components and service
structures from them and then basically
generate adapters that can adapt to the
legacy systems of course that
doesn't always work so sometimes you
would also want to describe the
interfaces manually and then either
generate a legacy adapter component if
you have formal mapping from your new
interfaces to the old stuff or in the
worst case consider the adaptation to
the legacy components or to the legacy
stuff as an implementation detail and do
it manually before we finally talked a
little bit about business process
modeling let's talk about the spaghetti
misunderstanding do you know what I mean
I know the large forgetting like monster
but that's the spaghetti incident but
that's all yeah anyway so the spaghetti
misunderstanding is as follows you
probably have all seen these pictures
where you have this big bowl of mud with
a lot of you know typically bullets or
systems which everybody depends on
everybody and you know you have these
interconnections from everybody to
everybody else so you have this
spaghetti kind of system and then you
have this other diagram which is
typically labeled
SOA where you have a number of systems
which are nicely arranged around a
central thing which is usually called
the enterprise service bus and what this
thing wants to tell you is if you do an
SOA with a neatly defined enterprise
service bus then the many-to-many
dependencies of the previous spaghetti
like architecture are resolved into
clear one-to-one architectures because
only a dependencies because everybody
only depends on the enterprise service
bus and that picture kind of suggests
that you should have only one enterprise
service bus with basically one
middleware every you have to agree in
the whole enterprise on one middleware
and people then typically say it has to
be web services and that's of course
complete crap first of all web services
are usually not really the best thing
many of the enterprise service bus is
used middle world like for examples tip
code stuff or other JMS based
implementations which is at least as
good as web services web services are
good for external services but not
necessarily necessarily within an
enterprise the other thing is that the
really important thing is not that
physically at runtime there is only one
middleware what is important is that
your services and data structures are
described designed in a way
models which allows you to generate
mappings of those data structures and
interfaces for all kinds of technologies
because if you have a communication
between services which is kind of
real-time critical then it's usually not
a good idea to use web services there
are just simply faster protocols or more
efficient protocols in general if our
example you want to be open and
standards-based and communicate with
this Microsoft application on the other
side of your enterprise then it's
probably good to use Web Services so the
really essential point is not that you
have one physical middle word technology
in your enterprise and standardize on
this thing but rather that all your
applications dependencies and data
structures are designed in a way that
allowed that have so he have logically
only this one thing right this logical
bus but at runtime it can easily be
implemented using various technologies
and you can generate the necessarily the
necessary mappings yeah and I think the
the thing that is quite important about
that as well is that you can actually
have no middleware at all yes that your
call is it's actually mapped on a normal
call a Java call or whatever it is some
mythical and that it's not that is also
important in terms of performance
because yes it's a call that isn't
removed yeah and that doesn't have the
XML parsing and marshalling and so on so
you have like real time critical things
you would co-locate your components in
the same process and they can't
communicate locally yeah and I mean it's
also you know the first law of
distributed objects by Fowler just don't
distribute yeah and that's basically
that's basically why this is probably
really important because it allows
should have an SOA even though you don't
distribute your objects at least not all
of them not all of them so the point is
just you will have different quality of
service requirements for different
communication paths right so and you
want to choose your middleware based on
these non-functional quality of service
requirements you shouldn't be far
into a middle world just because some
you know strategic see whatever Oh
decided that everything's going to be
done with Web Services now yeah and it's
also not I mean if you look at companies
out there in real life at least until
they during that transfer transition
phase towards the big unified SOA
middleware they'll have this scenario
where they have multiple different a
middleware some places will always have
the scenario business because as soon as
they migrated to the big so our
middleware there's going to be some
other big so our middleware on the
horizon which some big company is going
to try to sell you on so it's going to
change and that goes back to the point
that I think that these central models
and central the scripture should be
technology independent and you should
define them you should define the meta
models and not be dependent on your
vendors yeah and it also I mean in the
real world out there usually the IT
infrastructure of a company is quite
heterogeneous yeah and and will always
be yeah I'm just wondering whether there
is any company that ever succeeded in
doing homogeneous IT ok should we talk a
little bit about business process
modeling okay so I'm supposed to say yes
okay so yes yes yes thank you yes sir
III okay so business processes first of
all what's a business process it's
basically a process description a
process that and that is important runs
over a long time it's not like an
embedded systems where you use state
machines to control on the milliseconds
level you know your devices but business
processes are something that run over a
long time so the state of a business
process and all its data must be
persistent typically also executing a
business process and that's something we
talked about in the previous episode
extensively accesses the services
defined as part of your as a way and
since it does that it's a natural
layering that the process layer is on
top of the service layer okay so there
are two questions then how do you
describe services as sorry how do you
describe process
and how do you implement them there are
various ways of how they can be
described I would claim that about 80%
of all companies just could use simple
state charts in order to describe
services they don't need any business
process fancy modeling language of
course you can also use activity
diagrams UML then there is the business
process modeling notation that's
something more fancy and more recent and
we'll probably talk about this and
people and all these other things in
subsequent episodes I'm just wondering
how many subsequent episodes were going
to have oh we'll have software
engineering radio for the next 10 years
I think I don't know anyway okay okay
and then there are things like EP case
you know from IDs shale Germany
what is apk standing for Agnes Cousteau
the port's eschaton event-driven process
chains whatever so that's one aspect you
have to decide how you describe them how
you model them the other thing is how
you execute them typically you will
usually try to interpret these
definitions at runtime in Auto so you if
you change your business process
definition you don't have to redeploy
your whole system you know that the
whole the whole idea is that the process
is changed more often than the services
I'm not sure that this is actually true
so in the world that we've built
you know components interfaces models
there are two ways how you can implement
the execution of business processes one
is called you understand using process
components the other one uses an
external engine so let's first of all
look at process components the idea is
really simple what you do is that you
extend your meta model which contains
the notion of a component and you add a
subtype which is probably called process
component and the only there are two
there is only one difference from a
process component to an ordinary
component and that is that the
implementation of the component is not
something to implement manually but
rather this process component derives
its implementation code for
some kind of business process
description using statecharts activity
diagrams BPMN or EP case just what we
talked about before so and then since
components always have interfaces such a
process component typically has to
define at least one interface which is
probably called a process interface and
that you know if we stay in the example
of statecharts would have a void
operation for all the events or for all
the triggers for all the trigger events
that the state child can process so
that's basically all and then you would
basically draw the process for example
in UML you would associate this state
child with a process component and then
you run your generator and it either
generates the implementation completely
I mean there are 5000 different
strategies of how to implement a state
machine or you can just generate some
XML for example people that is then
executed as part of an interpreter for
for these kind of state state machines
that is encapsulated in your process
component so what you're saying is that
it's just a more specialized component
that we are talking about absolutely
takes the it's behavior from some kind
of a business process definition right
so I always have advocate then that
instead of trying to come up with this
generic business logic implementation
language like action semantics some
party or some people are talking about
I'd rather try to identify certain kinds
of typical behaviors in your enterprise
business rules yeah validations and
processes and then you would define a
specific notation for that particular
kind of behavior and you would have a
business rule component a validation
component a GUI component and the
process component and the implementation
of the process component would be
described using a suitable process
description notation and then instead of
implementing your component manually as
is the case with general purpose
components you would generate the
components implementation derived on the
business process description that you've
described somewhere and there are
various details we could talk about but
we shouldn't go into too much details
without this without you know in a
visual way of describing things the
other way is that you consider business
processes something letters that is
basically outside the scope of your
component service thing so you basically
by an external business process engine
there various products on the market you
can describe business processes using
for example BPMN and then you would use
for example your services and there for
example web service definitions WSDL
which you would generate from your
models in order to access those services
as part of the process execution and in
that case as i said the process
execution is basically outside the scope
of your component architecture is going
to be a separate tool separate engine
you would why do you want to do this
maybe because there is nice graphical
editors for the business people to draw
their processes maybe you also have
legacy systems that you can attach to
with these machines without them being
components and also since these engines
typically interpret their process
definitions you probably the idea is
that you're a more agile with regard to
process changes of course the
disadvantage is that you have now
something that is completely different
from your component service interface
world so I would kind of recommend to
use the first approach and try to
implement your services as this
specialized form of component I've made
some really good experiences with that
although depending on the forces the
second alternative might also be useful
how do i integrate these processes then
with my components because those
components still need to trigger the
processes right yeah I mean of course
the the the engine has to provide some
interface with which somebody else can
trigger the processes that it hosts that
depends on the specific technology but
then I would basically say execute this
process or trigger this event which
which is much like the do it
I know yes do it open parenthese
stranger close friend it really depends
on the process engine because it could
also generate a specific web service
interface WSDL file for each of the
services you describe there and then you
could read this file and build your
model from it and then generate proxy
components okay I mean but of course
then of course some of the agility that
you get for the interpretation is you
know going through the roof because then
you have to regenerate stuff if you
change the process and basically you
bake to the to the first alternative yes
and that's why I'd suggest if you don't
have you know very specific reasons for
using the second one I'd really suggest
to use the first alternative and just to
you know give you a taste of how much
effort this is in a project we've
basically it has taken us two or three
days to go from general purpose
components to having persistent
long-running business process components
whereas the process was described with
with with the state child's so it's it's
not a big deal of work if you have the
other things in place and and you you
you know your world stays homogeneous if
a component wants to use another service
Pacific process if it wants to trigger a
process or even instantiate a process
and start it it's just a component
dependency in this case to a process
component okay yeah I mean I'm even
wondering why you're mentioning the
signature or just because some pub some
people do it and because there are tools
on the market and I want to just try to
explain the difference so you're
basically saying this is something that
happens out there in real life yeah even
though I don't like it even though in
most cases I would prefer the other
approach okay I see but can you think
about any reasons the company might have
used the respective processing process
description tools for five years for
example okay okay a non-technical
reasons mostly yes or technical reasons
could be if you want to integrate with
all kinds of strange legacy systems and
these engines bring adapters you know
that's
I might not want to do manually okay
okay before we finish with this episode
with this rather long episode which will
probably you know split into two so our
2a and so are to be and what it's so a
two point one if you read this gap no
study where they said so uh is is kind
of all the old fashioned now that you
have to have so a two point zero and we
have SOA two point one and yeah so two
we are always ahead of the crowd and of
course for iam anyways so let's talk
about a couple of technologies finally
since we've talked only about concepts
okay data definition how do you define
data structures simple data structures
can simply be represented as nested
structs basically there is a language
called llamo yet another markup language
I guess YAML it's basically as I said
it's a way to describe nested structs
that's enough for four for simple data
structures more complex data structures
should be represented using XML of
course you have to consider some of the
performance issues you might want to
have binary representations of the xml
infoset to get some better performance
there in well it really depends depends
on whether this is the bottleneck if you
did use xml schema for data definition
the dtds are somewhat out you shouldn't
use them anymore if you want to access
these schemas more comfortably you can
generate binding classes so you have a
nice api towards your xml document of
course be careful warning the
interpretation advantage is lost if you
change the data structure you have to
regenerate your binding classes if you
use xml schema you should probably
restrict the power of xml schema quite a
bit because xml schema is really really
powerful for example there are various
ways of redefines import include stuff
namespace stuff and all this kind of
stuff you should really restrict that
otherwise things that are going to get
complicated and that's something that i
really speak about from experience so
you might want to use UML for example to
describe to define your data structures
and then generate the XML schema from
that and use
respective constraints on the UM our
model to make sure that the schema is
not going to be too complicated for the
communication middleware of course you
can use all kinds of middlewares there
is nothing specifically so uh of course
the hype says you have to use web
services currently WS interoperability
basic profile 1.1 is something that's
often used probably it's already
outdated by the time we broadcast this
episode as I said before W STL 1.1 is
not enough it's really not enough
because it only describes one service
from the viewpoint of the provider and
that really no deployment information it
has no reverse dependencies it's not
enough in WSDL 2.0 things will get a
little bit better as I mentioned before
and that's again you shouldn't try to
use WSDL as your master definition
format for your so ah use your own
models build your own repository and of
course you can then generate WSDL from
that in order to generate some kind of
web service proxies don't build those
generators yourself just generate the
WSDL but don't take the WSDL as your
master of course there are other
infrastructures you can use you can use
Carbaugh Java RMI dotnet remoting indigo
in the messaging world you can use jam
as MQ series MSM q-tip cost products
whatever how do you decide first of all
probably there's already something there
so you should consider that and then of
course you will probably have some non
functional requirements that will guide
your decisions runtime platforms for
your components there are all kinds of
alternatives j2ee of course servlets
each Abi's message driven bean message
driven bean spring is a good candidate
you can run your components on OSGi or
eclipse on windows communication
foundation Kham Kham plus all that stuff
SCA the important point again is
implement your components independent of
the patterns and idioms of this
technology and map them using generated
code from the respective deployment
models of course the choice of the
runtime platform platform should be
guided by
experience of course and non-functional
requirements there is also a new breed
of so our component platforms which is
basically Java business integration and
the SCA the service component
architecture both are really still
bleeding-edge standards are sometimes
not even yet finished we'll very briefly
I'll say something about jbi and SCA and
then we'll we'll probably have
additional episodes in the future let's
talk about jbi and SCA so jb is
basically short for a java business
integration is the java standard tears
are I don't know it's a middleware
middleware so it provides unified view
on various middleware systems and it
Maps the communication between
components to standardized message
formats the so called normalized message
and then it routes those messages among
the various components in a jvi
container there are two kinds of
components there are service engines
which implement business logic or
transformations and binding components
which basically serve as adapters to
external middleware such as web services
services described our are described in
WSDL more specifically they use the
abstract message definitions from WSDL
to and of course the point is currently
most jbi containers are still local and
that's not very useful but distributors
jbi implementations are becoming
available as we speak my personal
opinion there I am really skeptical
about jbi because I'm missing you know
the system view it doesn't talk about
deployment and composition and all that
kind of stuff it just basically again is
a kind of more fancy way of implementing
a component and its server it isn't more
like an Enterprise Service bus no it
depends officially not because I mean
you can build one because if if you have
a distributed jbi implementation then
this can serve as an Enterprise Service
bus although that the notion of
Enterprise Service bus is usually
considered something different it's
basically a it's basically message
driven middleware but I mean basically
what reveaied us as far as I know is
that it generates these normalized
messages and integrate into
each and every system into that plus an
engine that somehow executes business
processes and does other ABI it would be
one of those service engines right right
and so therefore it's basically an
integration platform yes it's not for
containers yeah anyway yeah
okay yeah but the point is it you know
it doesn't talk about deployment it
doesn't there's no description for
composition there is no reverse
dependency tracking you know there is no
data domain scoping there is all the
issues we talked about before aren't
addressed by by jbi that's basically
what I meant it's just another
infrastructure yes but it doesn't do the
whole thing there and also it's it's
Java specific I mean what's the point
I mean if we say that that that the NSA
way is enterprise wide and if you want
some you know so our middleware then
what's the point of defining a Java
specific infrastructure I don't get it
so and the reason why I'm saying all
that is because I think that SCA is much
better in there so SCA is an upcoming
standard it's currently I think it's
version 0.9 0.9 it's developed by IBM as
IP Oracle BA Sybase I thought that Sun
is already also part of the game and and
and abroad I think in the first 21 is
also in there yeah actually we are also
part of the SCA sanitization right so so
what is SCA it's basically it's
basically kind of exactly what we talked
about in this episode it talks about
components about component instances
that are connected and there are
interfaces that the components provide
and use you can define modules which
basically contain component instances
and you describe all these things of
course with XML so you might want to
have nice modeling front ends on top of
that but the point is that SCA really
doesn't just define components and their
service but also looks at all the
deployment and composition aspects we
talked about before so for me it looks
much more interesting than jbi because
it considers the whole system and not
just you know just another service
provisioning infrastructure which
kind of boring we've had that five
million times so jbi is just another
implementation of this approach okay so
should we add another two minutes and
kind of summarize what we talked about
and then call it a day yeah okay okay
first of all oh it's an interesting
sentence it says so is about it's not
about technology it's also not about
business so it's first and foremost
about architecture you might disagree
yeah well I mean it's I would rather say
that it's about business but I mean we
had the whole episode right we spent on
there's two different sides mm-hmm it's
probably the different perspectives what
I'm saying is it's driven by business
yes
and what you're saying is its
implemented by thinking about
architecture right and what we both
agree upon is that it's not really
technology driven yeah yeah okay so you
should keep all the important
information in models separated into
different concerns and their viewpoints
you should define your own meta model
because this is your strategic the
definition of your strategic
architecture your architecture
repository and that child should be
under your control you should consider
technology to be an implementation
detail and keep models as well as the
business logic implementations free from
technology of course you shouldn't build
your own communication middleware or
execution platform you should select the
suitable third-party stuff we talked
about this just in the last couple of
minutes however don't start with the
technology start with the concepts we
talked about and then map it to
technology once you're once you know
what your non-functional requirements
are consider your application developers
the primary user group of your SOA your
business people to be honest won't care
okay I mean even if it's business driven
you won't find your business manager
care about as a way really I mean it's
it's primarily the IT folks and the
application developers we have to work
with the SOA it again I think it depends
on on what you're looking at because
what what he cares about is about
it's the speed of development us you can
change according to the business
requirements okay and those those are
the reasons why we are pushing SOA in
the first place what you're saying again
is how you need to implement that by not
making by not forcing people to do it
but rather have them yeah
if their main easy way to do it and make
it there therefore easier to adopt it
yeah it's adopted make sure your service
implementations remain testable without
all the infrastructure considered
deployment operations and monitoring
another important stakeholders so you
should support these folks for example
by generating configurations for some
kind of IT management system you should
only standardize and harmonize were
absolutely necessary for example on the
meta level and maybe on the tool level
but not necessarily on the level of
concrete specific service and component
definitions integrate your BPM on top of
well-defined component architecture and
don't start with BPM okay anything else
you want to kind of say before before we
give up for today
are you going to put the presentation
presentation okay so yeah we okay we
admit right so this episode was based on
a set of slides that I did for various
conferences so yes I can I can put them
online yeah because that would basically
help from me yes yes okay thanks for
listening yeah and have a great day see
you next time bye
yeah here's your next time
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at SAE - radio dotnet
although we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website so other
people can see what you think
software engineering radio wants to
thank Henning poly for the intro and
outro music as well as Lipson for
providing the bandwidth this episode of
se radio as well as all other episodes
is licensed under Creative Commons
license see the software engineering
radio website for details